Norman Bogner Papers
Norman Bogner Papers
1959-2015
Bogner, Norman, 1935-
7.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American novelist, author. Includes writings (drafts, manuscripts, and galleys of novels, plays and screen plays), and memorabilia.
148856
Biographical History
Norman Bogner (1935- ) is an American author, editor and television writer.
Norman Bogner lived in Europe for 14 years. During this period, he worked at the publishing house Jonathan Cape as an editor and then as Editorial Manager. Among the many authors whose works he has edited are John Fowles, Edna O'Brien, Ronald Harwood, Arnold Wesker, C. Day Lewis, and A.W. Lawrence. He also edited Derek Walcott's first volume of poetry, two novels by Claude Simon, and Alan Paton's book of short stories, Debbie Go Home; these three gentlemen eventually won Nobel Prizes for Literature. Bogner's work has appeared in a number of magazines and his reviews have appeared in the Sunday Times and the Times Literary Supplement.
Bogner eventually left publishing for ABC-TV (later Thames-TV) and ran "Armchair Theatre," an anthology drama series comparable to "American Playhouse." He was responsible for over 100 hours of network television, and discovered and commissioned a number of then-unknown writers, including Tom Stoppard, Alan Ayckbourne, Charles Wood, and the late Dennis Potter.
His novel Seventh Avenue (1968) was a best-seller, and sufficiently successful that Bogner was at last able to devote himself to writing full time. His other novels include The Madonna Complex, Making Love, and California Dreamers. His books have sold 22 million copies worldwide, and Seventh Avenue was adapted as a six hour mini-series for NBC. Bogner has also written several plays for both theatre and television.
Bogner's wife, Felice Gordon, is an author and theatrical agent. They have three sons.
[Biographical sketch adapted from the author's website, 2007.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Norman Bogner Papers consist of correspondence, writings and memorabilia of the American author, editor and television writer.
Correspondence consists mostly of discussions about book signings and appearances.
Writings includes drafts, galleys, published editions of novels, plays, speeches, short stories, and screenplays. The collection also contains publicity and reviews of many of his works.
Memorabilia consists of scrapbooks, clippings, and assorted miscellany.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical order by title or topic.
Separated Material
Published editions of several books have been traferred to Rare Books for cataloging; these are noted in the inventory below. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Popular culture; Literature -- American Fiction; Bogner, Norman, 1935-; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Motion picture authorship.; Clippings (information artifacts); Compact discs.; Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Scrapbooks.; Scripts (documents); Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Norman Bogner, 1969, 2011-2018.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1997-1998; 2001,; 2005-2008,; undated; most relates to book signings and appearances; includes numerous guest lists; 2 folders (Box 11)
- Writings
  - Novels
    - 99 Sycamore Place
      - Published edition, 2009
        Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging; please refer to to locate this item.
    - Arena
      - Original manuscript, 1978; 5 folders (Box 1)
      - Correspondence and publicity, 1979 (Box 1)
    - California Dreamers
      - Correspondence, publicity, dustjacket, 1981 (Box 1)
      - Publicity, reviews, etc. (Box 11)
    - The Criminal Chronicles
      - Typescript (A), 2015; bound; signed by Bogner (Box 2)
      - Typescript (B), bound in 3 parts; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Typescript (C), 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Feb 5, 2010 Final Draft of The Criminal Chronicles, bogner_n_001; Post-It note on jewel case says "NB Final Draft April 23, 2010." File formats unknown; when viewed on workstation, CD appeared to be blank ("This folder is empty"); CD (Box 9)
    - The Deadliest Art
      - 1st draft, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Published edition, 2001
      - Publicity, reviews, etc. (Box 11)
    - Divorce
      - 1st draft, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The Fate of Sandcastles
      - Typescript (A), 2015; bound; signed by Bogner (Box 3)
      - Typescript (B), undated; noted on title page as "Author's Copy" and signed by Bogner; pp. 1-300; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Typescript (B), cont., undated; noted on title page as "Author's Copy" and signed by Bogner; pp. 301-429 (Box 10)
      - Typescript (C), undated; 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Typescript (D), undated; 3 folders (Box 10)
    - The Fox's Teeth
      - Typescript, before Sep 2016; signed by Bogner; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Honor Thy Wife
      - Author's draft, 2000 (Box 3)
      - Author's draft (cont.), 2000 (Box 4)
      - Jacket photo, 1999 (Box 4)
      - Published edition, 1999
      - Publicity, reviews, etc. (Box 11)
    - The Hunting Animal
      - Published edition, 1974
    - In Spells No Longer Bound
      - 1st draft, 1959 (Box 4)
      - Author's copy, 1961 (Box 4)
      - Jacket photo, 1958 (Box 4)
    - The Madonna Complex
      - 1st draft, 1968 (Box 4)
      - Printer's copy with revisions, undated (Box 4)
      - Printer's copy with revisions (cont.), undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Galley proof with corrections, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Galley proof with corrections (cont), 1968 (Box 5)
      - Published edition, 1968
    - The Madonna Complex, 2000 revision
      - Notes, 1999 (Box 5)
      - Author's final draft, 1999 (Box 5)
      - Author's final draft (cont.), 1999 (Box 6)
      - Author's copy with corrections, 1999; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Corrected proof copy, 2000 (Box 6)
      - Publicity, reviews, etc. (Box 11)
    - Making Love
      - Published copy, 1971
      - Publicity, reviews, etc. (Box 11)
    - Seventh Avenue (previously published as Divorce)
      - Published edition, Corgi, 1968
      - Published edition, Dell, 1975
    - Spanish Fever
      - 1st draft, 1961 (Box 6)
      - Corrected proof copy, 1962 (Box 6)
      - Published edition, Longmans, 1963
      - Published edition, New American Library, 1968
    - To Die In Provence
      - Original manuscript, undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Uncorrected bound manuscript, 1998 (Box 7)
      - Publicity, reviews, etc., 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Plays
    - The Waiters, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Screenplays
    - Master of the Signs (Box 11)
    - Privilege, circa 1966 (Box 7)
    - Privilege, publicity and reviews (Box 11)
  - Short stories
    - Fragments [this is the actual title of the story] (Box 11)
    - Michael Swap III, notes only (Box 11)
    - Slaughterhouse, includes notes and feedback from a Roger D. (Box 11)
  - Speeches
    - Book talk (Box 11)
    - Dutton talk (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Fragments and unidentified (Box 11)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, 1967-1987 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks, 1968-1981; 6 volumes (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous, includes cover of book by Bogner's wife, Felice Gordon (Box 11)